Inventory of the Jiri Setina Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Jiri Setina Collection
1945-1996
94021
Setina, Jiri, collector.
39 manuscript boxes (15.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photocopies of selected minutes, reports, memoranda, and letters, of the central committee of the Czechoslovak communist party and the Czechoslovak ministry of the interior, relating to political persecutions in Czechoslovakia, trials and imprisonment for political offenses, forced labor camps, confiscation of church property, and secret police activities.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1994.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Originals in: Archiv Komunisticke strany *Ceskoslovenska, Prague, and Archiv Ministerstva vnitra, Prague.
Scope and Content of Collection
Photocopies of selected minutes, reports, memoranda, and letters, of the central committee of the Czechoslovak communist party and the Czechoslovak ministry of the interior, relating to political persecutions in Czechoslovakia, trials and imprisonment for political offenses, forced labor camps, confiscation of church property, and secret police activities
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Political prisoners--Czechoslovakia.; Forced labor--Czechoslovakia.; Secret service--Czechoslovakia.; Civil rights--Czechoslovakia.; Political crimes and offenses--Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Religion.; Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo vnitra.; Komunistická strana *Ceskoslovenska. Úst*redni výbor.
Container List
- Minutes of meetings of the Presidium of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the case of churches, dignitaries, priests, religion teachers, former theology students, nuns and monks, and the group Russicum; memorandum of a congregation of the Catholic bishops to the president of the Czech Republic; reports of the Czechoslovak Communist Party Regional Committee for Church Affairs relating to the case of Czech and Slovak nuns, the ten accused clerics, the surveillance of church services in Prague in 1949, the removal of archbishop Josef Beran, and the working plan of 1949 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- List of employees transferred from the Department of National Defense to the regional committees of the National Institute for Church Affairs; proposal of the Central Action Committee of the National Front for the reorganization of the group Junák; reports relating to the cases of the group Russicum, activities of the Christian-Democratic Party deputy František Kaďůrek, the lawsuit against bishop Stěpán Trochta and his punishment, the punishment of priests, and the purge of churches in 1950; statute of the pioneer division of the group Junák (Folder 1: 2)
- List of prisoners in the forced labor camp Mírov; report on removal of residents and unreliable individuals from the restricted border zone; minutes of meetings of the Presidium of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party. (Folder 1: 3)
  Includes the speech of Rudolf Slanský about the burial of Edvard Beneš in September 1948
- Report on the status of the Czechoslovak security system and trial and imprisonment for political offenses (Folder 1: 4)
- Written agreement between the Central Customs Office and the 4th sector of the Corps of National Security on the cooperation in non-tradable imports and exports; written request from the Italian Communist Party for financial help to organize a courier service between Warsaw, Budapest, and Bucharest (Folder 1: 5)
- Minutes of meetings of the Political Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party, relating to the origin of The 2000 Words Declaration, its authors and organizers, the proposal on the observation of illegal groups and their activities, and the internal political situation in August 1989; plans, letters and notes about the situation of the National Security Department; situation report on employees, the Department of Education, forced labor camps, the People's Militia, rifles, and the organization of the Corps of National Security; complaint against employees of the Company Baťa; working guide for the verification of citizens and purge of the republic of enemies; note of the Security Commission consultant; report on Czechoslovak refugees, the detention of the West German secret service agent Libuše Hrubá (Soňa), and on the investigation methods of Milan Moučka; proposals of Alexej Cepička to fill positions on the regional and provincial Security Commission and to reduce Soviet consultants in the Department of Interior; second part of the minutes of meeting of the Soviet Central Committee of the Communist Party relating to the Soviet-Yugoslav treatment (Folder 1: 6)
- Reports on death penalty trials, the Czech agent Stefan Kolman, who was shot to death by Oldřich Kvapil, criminal methods of the National Security Department in 1948 and 1949, the elimination of an illegal agrarian organization, executions of Miloslav Choc and Slavoj Sádek, trials and imprisonment for political offenses, and the Czechoslovak Counter-Intelligence Service; complaint against Jaromir Kopecký (Folder 1: 7)
- Reports on the escaped prisoner Jan Hvasta hiding in the American embassy, the liquidation of the group Odborník, and trials and imprisonment for political offenses (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Reports on the detention of demonstrators on 1962 May 1, purges in central authorities, the status of the National Security Department in 1969, foreign broadcasting jamming, the events of 1988 December 9–11, and security during celebrations in church sv. Víta in Prague in 1988; minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party; directives of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party (Folder 2: 2)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses and the removal of unreliable individuals from Prague (B operation) (Folder 2: 3)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses, the removal of residents and unreliable individuals from the restricted border zone, and the censoring of letters and telegrams from and to capitalist countries; proposal on the dissolution and prohibition of Zionist organizations in Czechoslovakia and the nomination of a head prosecutor in the Rudolf Slanský trial (Folder 2: 4)
- Letter from the Department of Foreign Affairs to the American embassy relating to the kidnapping of Czechoslovak agents in West Germany; proposal of the Department of Interior on confiscated houses released to Germans with Czechoslovak citizenship; reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses (Folder 2: 5)
- Reports of the Consulting Committee of the National Security Department on the verification of citizens (T-43 operation) and the trial for Věkoslav Loutský and Miroslav Pich-Tůma; letter from Karel Košťál to Antonín Novotný about his party activities; list of employees of the Regional Security Committee; directives of the Department of National Security, Department of Interior, and the Department of Justice on the situation of families of convicted kulaks (Folder 2: 6)
- Reports on the conference of deputies of the Committee for Church Affairs with Soviet ministries, the burials of bishop Karel Skoupý, bishop Robert Pobožný, and bishop Josef Hlouch, the confiscated American religious movie Youth in Trouble, religious ceremonies for Virgin Marie Svatohorská, the confiscation of Gestapo documents from Bohumil Siebert, and the reorganization plan of the National Security Department; list of individuals killed while attempting to cross the border in the years 1948-1956 (Folder 2: 7)
- Reports on political trials for Antonín Prchal and Karel Košťál and on activities of Soviet consultants; statement of Dagmar Marešová on the use of violence during interrogations; letter from Karel Košťál to Antonín Novotný; appeal to join the Czechoslovak Secret Service; correspondence between Klement Gottwald, Filipov, and Joseph Stalin (Folder 2: 8)
- List of employees of the 4th sector of the Department of Interior; statements of Department of Interior employees relating to the trials of Rudolf Slanský, Marie Svermová, and Otto Sling (Folder 2: 9)
- Record of an interview with Ladislav Kopřiva in 1963; statements of Department of National Security employees on the use of violence during interrogations of prisoners and on Ladislav Kopřiva; reports on trials for political offenses (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses and the displacement of German citizens; proposal on the observation of employees of the Department of National Security (Folder 3: 2)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses, the removal of the statue of T. G. Masaryk in Prostějově, and the trial for French and French-American spies (Folder 3: 3)
- List of functionaries of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party; minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to contacts with socialist countries; list of Czechs honored with medals (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; minutes of meetings on activities of the Corps of National Security, the border guards, and the troops under the Department of Interior in 1986 and 1990 (Folder 4: 2)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; list of Czechs honored with medals; proposal on dispatching a delegation of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party to Bulgaria; decision on crime reduction; report on border protection policy in 1987; proposal on dispatching employees of the National Security Department, soldiers, and fire fighters to Russian universities, and on activities of the Corps of National Security, the border guards, and the troops under the Department of Interior in 1986-1990 (Folder 4: 3)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; proposal on dispatching a delegation of the Department of Interior to Cuba, Poland, and Hungary; minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to contacts with socialist countries; list of Department of Interior employees honored with medals (Folder 4: 4)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; proposal to dispatch a delegation of the Department of Interior to Poland, Bulgaria, and the Soviet Union; plan for meetings of leading functionaries of the Department of Interior (Folder 4: 5)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; plan for meetings of leading functionaries of the Department of Interior; list of Department of Interior employees honored with medals; minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the dispatching of employees of the National Security Department, soldiers, and fire fighters to Russian universities (Folder 4: 6)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; proposal on a visit of a delegation of the Department of Interior to Yugoslavia, Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, the Soviet Union, Poland, Afghanistan, and Iraq, and the organization of the national day of the Corps of National Security in 1981; plan for foreign meetings of leading functionaries of the Department of Interior; list of employees of the Corps of National Security honored with medals (Box-folder 5: 1)
- List and personnel files of Czech and Slovak students in Russian academies; plan for foreign meetings of leading functionaries of the Department of Interior; personnel files of the Department of Interior; minutes of meetings relating to the dispatching of employees of the National Security Department, soldiers, and fire fighters to Russian universities; proposal on a visit of a delegation of the Department of Interior to Yemen, Mozambique, Angola, Zambia, and the Soviet Union (Folder 5: 2)
- Proposal on a visit of a delegation of the Department of Interior to Vietnam, Laos, Poland, Guinea, and Guinea-Bissau; personnel files of the Department of Interior; plan for foreign meetings of leading functionaries of the Department of Interior; report on the political and moral position of employees of the Corps of National Security, border guards, and soldiers of the troops under the Department of Interior; list of employees of the Department of Interior honored with medals (Folder 5: 3)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior; proposals on the organization of the national day of the Corps of National Security in 1981, and a visit of a delegation of the Department of Interior to Iraq, Afghanistan, and Yugoslavia; list of employees of the Corps of National Security, border guards, and soldiers honored with medals; plan for foreign meetings of leading functionaries of the Department of Interior (Folder 5: 4)
- Reports on the secret agent Stephan Kollmann, shot to death by the Czech general Oldřich Kvapil, including testimonies, newspaper clippings, list of individuals with nicknames, and documentation about the frontier book of the 16th company frontier guard (Box-folder 6: 1)
- Map with numbers of prisons and forced labor camps in Czechoslovakia in 1952; reports on three dead refugees, the trial of the former captain of the Corps of National Security Miroslav Pich-Tůma (nickname Tomáš), and the Masna operation, including testimonies (Folder 6: 2)
- Report on the death of cleric Josef Toufar and Ladislav Zelenka; testimonies on interrogation methods (Folder 6: 3)
- Personnel files of the Department of Interior
  - 1968-1978 (Folder 6: 4)
  - 1980 (Folder 6: 5)
  - 1981-1982 (Folder 6: 6)
  - 1983-1984 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Report of the Superior Military Court on the trial of Osvald Závodský, Ivo Milen, Oskar Valeš, Vladimir Smolka, Bedřich Pokorný, Miroslav Pich-Tůma, and Karel Cerný (Folder 7: 2)
- List of prisoners, including their date and place of birth, address, time and reason for imprisonment, behavior, state of health, etc. (Folder 7: 3)
- Report on trials and imprisonment for political offenses and the transfer of Czechoslovak army officers to the forced labor camp Mírov; proposal on the dissolution and prohibition of Zionist organizations; minutes of meetings of the Political Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia; list of convicted functionaries of Czech and Slovak political parties; law relating to forced labor camps; working program for the verification of citizens and purge of enemies from the republic (T-43 operation) (Folder 7: 4)
- Proposals on the surveillance of employees of the Corps of National Security and the purge of the children of kulaks from agricultural schools; report on administrative actions against kulaks; directive of the Department of National Security, Department of Interior, and Department of Justice on the situation of families of convicted kulaks; directives for the transfer of the families of convicted kulaks (Folder 7: 5)
- Private archive of Karel Klos, minister of justice; statute of the pioneer division of the group Junák (Folder 7: 6)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses and the control of public and private storage depots in the country; proposals on the amnesty of Vilém Stanovský and new forced labor camps regulations (Folder 7: 7)
- List of individuals involved in the Rudolf Slánský trial; reports on the torture of four prisoners, trials and imprisonment for political offenses, security in the Prague region, the trial of Antonín Hašek, and the Koloďeje operation; personnel files of party members; proposal to fill positions on the regional and provincial security commission; interview with Ladislav Kopřiva; minutes of meetings of the Political Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the National Security Department; letter of Antonín Novotný about Ladislav Kopřiva, Jaroslav Hora, and circumstances in the headquarters of the National Security Department (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Reports on activities of the 1st sector between 1949 and 1954, the 2nd sector (including a list of employees who tortured people during interrogations between 1948 and 1954), sector 2a, the 3rd sector, and the BA (a 4th sector of the Department of Interior), security in the Prešov region, and trials and imprisonment for political offenses; minutes of meetings of the Political Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the Department of National Security; directive of the Department of National Security, Department of Interior and Department of Justice on the situation of families of convicted kulaks; proposals on the purge of the children of kulaks from agricultural schools, the creation of a Central Committee of the Slovak Communist Party Department for Defense, Security, and Justice, the reorganization of the protection of government and party members, and of the minister of national security on the cooperation between party and security organs; reports on Josefa Slánská, Eliška Frejková, Jiřina Franková, Ludmila Clementisová, Jožka Reicinová, Marie Svabová, Lise Ricol Londonová, Karla Hajduová, Eliška Loeblová, Hedvika Margoliusová, Marie Fischlová, Marian Slingová, Lisa Simonová, Bedřich Adler, Anna Traute Slánská, Lisa Hašková, Jarmila Kryslová, Robert Alt Bartek, Antonín Patejdl, Vilém Kún, Ludmila Neufusová, and Jiřina Kopoldová; final reports on the cases of Richard Slánský, Gejza and Charlotta Pavlík, Alice Kohn (Glasner), Oskar Kosta, Karel Markus, Rudolf Egon Feigl, Dora Klein, Vlasta Veselý, Goldstuecker, Antonín Kavan, Dufek, Vojta Jančík, Eduard Outrata, Josef Mirovský, and Mordechai Oren; activity report of the Office for Press Management; announcement of the Corps of National Security in 1952 (Folder 8: 2)
- Report on trials for political offenses; written request of Karel Mazanec for rehabilitation (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Lawsuit of the attorney general of the Czech Republic Jiří Setina against the former agent Pavel Minařík, and lawsuit relating to the complaint of Jan Antonín Baťa; personnel files of the Department of Interior; report on Ivan Fiala and the trial of Jan Antonín Baťa; secret report on Baron František Lobkowicz (Folder 9: 2)
- Statements of Karel Sváb and Otmar Kašina relating to the Slánský trial, of Bohumil Klícha relating to the Department of Agriculture Commission, of Jaroslav Hora relating to activities of the Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party, and of Heda Synková relating to her activity in the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party; reports of commander Antonín Kavan on the 4th sector of the Department of Interior, the agent Petra Buzková (Pavla), and the Presidium of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party about the rehabilitation of prisoners; minutes of meetings of the Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to employees of the Department of National Security; application of Ivan Kočárník for membership in the Czechoslovak Communist Party (Folder 9: 3)
- Written request of Hans Heinrich Thun von Hohenstein for asylum in the Czechoslovak Republic; reports of the Political Bureau of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party on the transfer of Germans, activities of scientific and technological intelligence in 1957, the prohibition of foreign broadcasting, the arrest of thirty-six American agents, the detention of the West German secret service agent Libuše Hrubá (Soňa), and activities of West German intelligence and counter-intelligence organs; proposal of the Department of Interior on confiscated houses released to Germans with Czechoslovak citizenship; decision of the government for special help for Afghanistan in 1986–1990; record about an interview with Hana Nehamerová relating to the Pley operation; working plan of the Department of Interior against emigration (Folder 9: 4)
- Report on Reinhard von Gehlen; record about an interview of deputy Kudrny with Jindřich Veselý; minutes of the meeting of the Presidium and Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the situation of state security; directives of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party, and the use of prisoners in factory production (Folder 9: 5)
- Reports on the removal of residents and unreliable individuals from the restricted border zone, trials and imprisonment for political offenses, the statement of Otmar Kašina, and the removal of the statue of T. G. Masaryk in Prostějově; record of an interview with Václav Aleš; letter of Václav Nosek (Folder 9: 6)
- List of functionaries of the central organs of the Czechoslovak Communist Party in 1945-1989 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- Reports on the investigation of illegal departures of trains abroad, the investigation of railway routes to foreign countries, and the interrogation of Věra Máchová; personnel files of the Department of Interior; statistics about Czechoslovak refugees; minutes of meetings of the Political Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the use of prisoners in manufacturing (Folder 10: 2)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses, including the Slánský trial, activities of justice organs during the period of political processes, and the statement of Dagmar Marešová on the use of violence during interrogations; proposal of Alexej Cepička to fill positions on the regional and provincial security commission (Folder 10: 3)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses, the statement of Ladislav Niewald about his activity in the Department of Interior, the Koloďeje operation, the transfer of Germans, and the verification of citizens and purge of enemies from the republic (T-43 operation); letter of Antonín Novotný about Ladislav Kopřiva, Jaroslav Hora, and the situation in the National Security Department; record of an interview with Ladislav Kopřiva in 1963 (Folder 10: 4)
- Interview with Vladimír Kohoutek about activities of Soviet consultants; correspondence between Klement Gottwald, Filipov, and Joseph Stalin; report on the confiscation of Gestapo documents from Bohumil Siebert (Folder 10: 5)
- Reports on trials and imprisonment for political offenses (Folder 10: 6-8)
- Reports and interviews of Department of Interior employees relating to their activities (Box-folder 11: 1)
- Personnel files (minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party)
  - 1985 (Folder 11: 2)
  - 1986-1987 (Folder 11: 3)
  - 1988-1989 (Folder 11: 4)
- Minutes of meetings of the Central Committee of the Czechoslovak Communist Party relating to the dispatching of members of the Corps of National Security and soldiers to colleges in the Soviet Union (Box 12)
  - 1952–1954, 1963; 1965-1966 (Folder 12: 1)
  - 1972–1975 (Folder 12: 2)
  - 1976-1980 (Folder 12: 3)
  - 1981-1988 (Folder 12: 4)